so we're in the middle of the third of
the five meditations who can tell me the
first one
right
second one
yeah problems of trying to take care of
yourself by the way
again I repeat you can try
to keep doing that and it it's just not
going to work out so I mean I can save
you a lot of trouble in time
all right it's not gonna work out to
just take care of yourself it doesn't
work out
and you can either figure it out younger
or you can figure it out later
but you might as well save yourself the
trouble okay it just doesn't it never
works out to just pay attention to what
you want okay it just will it will fail
okay third one
yeah beautiful things that happen when
you really
take care of
and your thumb
okay good all right
my teacher is to say uh
you're supposed to take care of all
living beings and you are
a living being okay so don't think it
has to be you or them okay that's not
that's not the name of the game the game
is everyone
has an equal right to happiness and you
also have an equal right to happiness
so this Buddhist uh what do you call it
Buddhist self this self-suffering
Buddhist
is not not Buddhism
okay like hurting yourself to make
others happy is a is a dumb idea also it
does that doesn't work out either you
also quit after a while
uh okay so you might as well just take
care of everybody all right all right
including yourself
and I I have a lot of friends who are
good Buddhists
and they don't take care of themselves
and they they overdo it and they they
overwork themselves and then they quit
then they quit or they get sick and they
can't they can't continue so
you got to take care of yourself
you gotta stay healthy by the way and
then you otherwise you can't take care
of other people so
all right
um we're gonna go to the text you ready
Tim
uh so that
I like to go through the Tibetan uh
don't worry you can ignore it
and I'm just planting seeds for next
time okay so
you don't have to learn the Tibetan try
to pick up a few words it's okay
so pelki Day means
SRI
Sena SRI Sena
and that single line
we taught in Kyoto for I don't know a
week or something okay
so we went and found the story
of King SRI Sena
and I'll give you a picture who's doing
the pictures
uh
this is my brother
uh he's 72.
and
he has a project in Montana that he
works for and they caught firewood for
poor people
so they have a gang of uh what do you
call it
like guys who like to use big tools and
mess with stuff so they they cut wood
once a week
uh for poor people who just have stoves
wood stoves and uh
it's a perfect picture of what they did
to Sri Singh
okay they cut his body in half basically
with a chainsaw
uh and he offered
I think it's kind of significant
that he offered 50 of his body you know
and the story is he offered his the
lower part of his body and and he uh
allowed he begged people to cut his body
uh so that he could give his legs to a
person who didn't lower half of his body
50 50.
and we did that story in Kyoto in uh
basically
because of his desire
to share his own body 50 50.
uh his body was restored
and he was
physically happier and better than when
he started okay but uh and I
we paused the alarm Rim we we did one
line
in a whole Retreat and Tim was going
crazy
uh no because he saw it would take a
thousand years to finish the aluminum
and uh
but the story was so beautiful so we
translated the whole thing it's
available somewhere I don't know
uh you can read it if you want but it's
a beautiful beautiful story
and it and it just seemed to really fit
uh Kyoto Kyoto by the way is uh we chose
that City
rather than Tokyo because Kyoto
was laid out
as a Tang Dynasty City in around 1 400
years ago when the Tang Dynasty was big
in China and that's when Buddhism was
spending like wildfire in in China
central China so
Kyoto because of the cultural revolution
Kyoto is the last
Tang Dynasty city in the world it's more
Chinese than China
uh and a lot of Chinese people go there
to see there are seven
I think 70 000 temples in the in the
country there's a lot in the city
and uh it's a classical
uh Buddhist City
and it's very very beautiful so if you
have a chance to come to the programs in
Kyoto the Visas are extremely easy for
most almost all countries and uh and the
it's just a beautiful place the weather
is really beautiful and
the people are very gentle we were there
two weeks ago during Sakura which is
when the cherry blossoms open
and all the 20 year olds and 15 year
olds dress up in kimonos and I don't
know what's the guys kimono called
uh looks like Kung Fu outfit uh
but it's so beautiful and so graceful
and to be in a city
where honoring the cherry blossoms is as
important as the Super Bowl
is for Americans so imagine a whole
country
that gets excited about the cherry
blossoms
and all agents of people uh in the same
way that Americans get excited about the
Super Bowl
it's a really beautiful extremely
beautiful to be there and it's a great
place to study so ACI will be doing
lots of programs there you're welcome to
come big ones and small ones okay
I think this moments might be more sweet
than the big ones uh
so anyway uh
we finished that line and now Tim we're
going on
uh
so we're gonna start supna he gives
examples of other people
who made similar sacrifices in order to
uh
Dave in order to advertise how fun it is
to take care of other people's needs
okay
and and that's the section we're on
we're on the third section once we get
through that we'll be ready to start
exchanging ourselves and others okay
this is about a a bodhisattva who had a
uh suktor
uh a natural fleshy bump on their head
good one
and they cut it off as an offering to
someone else okay
uh tsuki Norbu means uh the jewel that
was naturally growing out of a bump on
their head
um
made a gift of it the next one
[Music]
very very famous story people ask me how
ACI started so here's the story
I guess it was 19.
probably
1991 or two or something like that
and I was in New York and uh
some people from a kagya tradition a
different tradition than songkapa they
asked me did
there was a group of about 20 of them
and they asked me to teach them 15.
they wanted to learn Tibetan because
they were going to do a three-year
Retreat and they wanted their their
llama asked them to be able to
do the prayers in tibetan
so they asked me to teach them to button
and so I thought well
since it's another tradition I should
teach them a Sutra because those are
accepted by all Traditions so I thought
nobody will get upset if I teach a Sutra
so I taught the Golden Light Sutra
Savannah prabha Sutra
and uh
which by the way is the national book of
Mongolia
just about and there's a story there
called doctor
means a female tiger Tigress
okay and lujin means to give your body
and the story is of a great bodhisattva
who's called ninto in tibetan
and that's mahasatva in Sanskrit
and that he was a mahasantha a great
being but his name his personal name was
also hey mahasa
and Greg courage his name was Greg
courage
and he was a prince he was out in the
forest he came across a
Tigress that was starving
and she was sick and she couldn't eat
and then she had four babies four Cubs
and they were trying to drink milk but
she didn't have any milk to give
and he saw that they would die and the
way it stated in the long room is
interesting uh
he says
means
she was desperate
because she was about to eat her own
cups she was coming close to
a situation
where to save one cup she would have to
eat another cup
so it's interesting I've never seen it
written that way
but she was close to eating one of her
own
comps to so she would have milk to feed
the other Cubs
this trends stopped
and decided to give her his body
and so he laid down next to her
and he took his shirt off you know and
he said eat me you know and she couldn't
she was too weak
and then there was a dead tree nearby
and he went and pulled a branch off and
he
he cut open his chest with the tree
branch he scratched scratched his chest
he got his chest nice and bloody
and then he laid down next to her and
let her lick the blood
and then gave her his body and he
as he was dying
he said but we're making a deal here
and if you eat my
flesh now
when I become a Buddha
you have to be my first student you five
have to be my first student
and then he died and she got
strong and she fed her babies and
and then later
they were the first five students of the
Buddha he became this Buddha Gautama
uh in this world and then uh his first
five
students uh the main the the first
the the eldest or the senior of the five
is called calvinia and
he taught them the four uh higher truth
he repeated it three times and they saw
emptiness they because of that hard
connection they had to him and The
Tigress was caldenia
and this is the story that's the first
teaching Lord Buddha ever gave
he didn't teach right away after he got
enlightened he waited some weeks
because he thought no one would
understand
and
you know as you guys
teach more and more which I hope you
will Hagerty uh as you teach more and
more
uh you will have this experience right
shin tin
that nobody understands anyway
[Music]
you keep going you know uh you just so
Lord Buddha uh after he got in line he
waited
he he wasn't sure it would help anybody
and he he refused to teach for some
weeks I think it was seven weeks and um
then they said well what the heck maybe
somebody will understand something uh
and he went and and started teaching so
that's the story of
The Tigress uh I think that was before I
started recording stuff I didn't know
but anyway those students uh we went
through the Golden Light Sutra we went
through that chapter about this story
and I taught it to them and then I I was
excited about the classes and I said
look I'm I'm hungry to teach emptiness
I'm hungry to teach higher subjects
uh and I but I but I grew up in a
different tradition I'm some company
tradition and and I said but I
I'd rather I'd rather teach some serious
classes and and ask your teacher if it's
okay
and if not you know I'm sorry but I
gotta teach emptiness I I can't teach
tiger stories for the rest of my life
and uh
so half of them had to quit their llama
said no I'd rather you didn't go
learn another tradition but half of them
uh I I kept them so I lost half my
students in one day it was very
traumatic
so I had six or seven students and
that's how we started ACI
and we started in a kitchen somebody's
kitchen and sitting around the table
like that so uh
that's the story how we started ACI so
if you're interested someday
it's a beautiful teaching from the
Golden Light Sutra the whole story okay
but I'm not going to tell the story or
Tim will kill me okay
[Music]
um
this is a famous person who gave away
their head
to somebody else okay
means and it means
this birth story okay
stories uh former lives of the Buddha
okay
okay so gay person means our llama
in that 24-day teaching
which this book is a record of
he taught those stories in detail how he
did that in 24 days I don't know
maybe they didn't have coffee breaks uh
okay uh
next uh
paragraphs and
[Music]
uh
means our teacher meaning Lord Buddha
who has great mahakuruna great great
compassion
look this is how
he got to be Buddha and by the way the
SRI the king that we studied in Kyoto
these are all former lives of Lord
Buddha right
right
is an old word temper Lots nowadays
they're saying not so
which means us guys
[Music]
means ourselves
uh passing means only ourselves Montauk
means nothing else
some means we think about we focused on
what we want okay uh
so for people who only are focused on
what they want these things would be God
difficult okay if you're
if your habit
is to take care of yourself first then
things like giving your body away would
be very difficult okay a young but
what's Muslim
yeah you can always
at our level
you know as you're doing your retreat
this week you can hear these stories
about people
by the way I wouldn't call it a
sacrifice
I would call it sharing the body they
had
okay so I I don't want you to think
that King SRI Cena
was giving up his body to another person
that's not the point and that's not why
they cut him exactly in half at the
waist
okay he didn't offer his legs to another
person
he recognized that other people had the
right to 50 of his body
you know equal right
okay and and it extends to your money
and your time
and your body
and and that
it's just a sign
that other people have equal rights
to your time and your money and your
attention Okay it's
it's very significant that he didn't
give his arm or his leg or or something
like that he gave exactly 50 of his body
okay because
he understood
that his body
there was equal rights to his body
okay I did my uh three year retreat in
the next Valley over
and there's uh nothing there there has
never been
anybody living there and the Animals
there are strange and uh the insects are
very strange and we had a butterfly a
moth like this big fluorescent green
would fly around
and uh
but there were uh silver mining there
and the tombstone is near there that's
where they had all the Cowboys shooting
each other
because they had rights to this line you
know this is your silver mine and this
is my silver mine in Doc Holliday and
Wyatt Earp and all these guys and wider
was digging near my retreat cabin
uh and uh so the the line was very
important
that that line
it's very important where does me stop
where does you start
and and they what they're saying is
even as you're meditating this week
you know there's no way
you can actually cut your body in half
happily
and and do that you know and
but you can pray
for the day okay you can pray for the
day and by the way there's a thing
called uh attention grabbing bodhisattva
attempts
uh
I'll give you an example my teacher
taught the story of melanepa
you know who ran off in his 50s to
Diamond Mountain to meditate for the
rest of his life and gave up his
business
and uh so my teacher taught it
we had this kind of
you know this young man in the class and
he so he packed up all his stuff
and he moved across the street
that there was a small Forest there you
know I
a few hundred yards of forest New Jersey
I mean
and uh
you know in between the super highways
and he went to live in this little patch
of forest you know because he heard
Miller rapist story
and my teacher said ah let him go he'll
be back in about three days
it took two days
and he came back he said that's hard
it's cold and my teacher's like yeah
you
it's kind of easier to meditate in the
house isn't it yeah yeah and uh
so don't do these uh grandstand they
call grandstanding right don't don't do
this
oh Buddha cut his body in half I'll cut
off a few fingers you know I've tried it
it's not the way to go okay
I I tried something like that it doesn't
work out okay just
slow and steady you know I the point is
not to do something
spectacular so that people pay attention
to you or something like that the point
is to quietly
uh share yourself with others in in the
people who are the best at it do it
invisibly you don't know they're doing
it but my wife is perfect example right
okay
um
so he says just this week
just pray
that you could reach a point
where you really recognize
that other people have an equal right to
your time
and to your attention uh okay and and
then slowly you'll start to
accommodate
their rights okay and don't try to do it
all in one day it doesn't work you know
just do it slowly
and again you have to expand your
capacity and you have to use emptiness
or you cannot serve all beings if you
understand emptiness if you see
emptiness directly you can personally
affect
every living being in the universe
directly face to face at the same time
okay and so
don't try it before that
you just go nuts
okay there will come a day
when you can serve every living being
directly
at the same time and that's what we're
working towards but you have to see
emptiness directly to do that okay
okay so it
so these people say oh I don't want to
study emptiness I want to study
compassion
that is compassion you know you you
can't be compassionate by the way now
there's Quail outside if you're
interested
who have this thing on the top of their
head and they always they always walk
around in families
with about 15 kids
they're very beautiful
okay
they got this thing on the top of their
head I don't know what that is
how that leads to survival I'm not quite
sure
okay uh
so here's a picture of a tiger with her
babies
uh
just think about it sometimes you know
this week
when you're doing your meditations
there will come a time
if you study emptiness well
that you can accommodate
everybody equally at the same time and
you have no limitations okay instead of
going crazy
to try to
accommodate 10 people with your limited
body
try to do it from the other direction
get a million bodies and then try to
accommodate three people
and uh
it's a lot easier and it's sustainable
okay don't try to
you know don't try to do with a limited
body you can't you cannot serve more
than a few people
but pray for more okay so the idea is
during this week think of the story of
Sri Senna if you don't have the story
I'm sure Tim can accommodate you
to get the story okay I translated the
whole story
and we handed it out for free
um go to Diamond Cutter press
diamondcutterpress.com
okay learning platform
okay I'm ACI
and and read it and just say yeah that
sounds good I would like to be able to
do that okay that's enough right now
and try to
be sensitive
that other people have an equal right to
happiness
and
there's sort of a radical
interpretation of that is that they have
an equal right to your time
as you do okay so think about just think
just cook it for a while
and you'll get you'll get good at it and
it's a wonderful that makes you happy
because then you
are doing what you know you're supposed
to be doing in this world why did you
come to this world we call it we did a
meditation in Kyoto for a Classic Soft
power this group business group from
China
and uh it was called mushroom meditation
uh
and it's a reference to the darn
mushrooms grow in the dark in the dark
means where were you before you came to
this world
and where are you going afterwards and
uh
and the dog is a lot longer than the
light
okay you have a certain number of years
between the two darknesses but there's a
huge darkness in the past and there's a
huge darkness in the future
and so you only have this time short
time
uh in the line to
to do something to do something with
your life and you will
run out of time time will run out it
doesn't matter how much yoga you do or
how many green drinks you green you
drink I mean the time is limited
in uh time will run out so do something
good with it do something worthwhile
with him the attempt
to serve yours your own immediate needs
is hopeless
your body will give out
you can't satisfy those needs you might
as well show yourself now while you have
a choice
because later you won't have a choice
okay so you between mushrooms
between the darkness before you came
here
duh where were you
or after you leave here duh where are
you going you might as well share
yourself while you're here you're not
here that long
you're not gonna miss out that much
stuff
you might as well make everybody happy
what's why not okay it's logical right
all right now he has another argument
for you and we're going to start at
Shenyang
okay
[Music]
means look
it makes Rapa means it makes sense
to take care of other people
okay
to have this kind of
cherishing
or sweet
sweet thinking about doing what other
people would like
rather than what you would like
okay he says
you know if you think about it
it's logical
well it means it's a logical that you
should do
you should take care of other people
not just yourself it's just logical
and and he says why they means I'll tell
you why
Berna
Panda means for example Jabra princess
uh
when you
how do you say
means the field where you grow crops
okay me and my wife drove to San Diego
we passed through all these
feels the fields used to
be close to Phoenix now you're going to
drive an hour to see a field but uh
apparentative
people
are like your feel okay if you want to
grow they're clearing some land over
here did you see
unfortunately I don't know what's going
to happen but uh they're gonna
try to grow some Orchards and a dairy I
think
some it's a foreign company I think uh
and they have cleared the
the land here made it nice and flat and
boring
and uh
so you need this kind of a sweet
open
rather fertile
soil to grow things okay you need that
all right
we spend a lot of time every spring to
prepare our garden it's tiny
you can walk across and in 10 or 15
Steps but it takes about uh two weeks to
prepare it for
for the summer it it takes about two
weeks to prepare the soil
so think of the soil like that okay well
prepared soil
uh
Denny says chintamani which is what
yeah I wish giving Jewel and this is the
full story is in lojong
sigima the eight verses there's a
beautiful description of a wishing Jewel
and this is a jewel that you find in a
stream for example
then there's a ritual you have to wash
it you have to
put it in silk cloth then on a certain
time of the Moon you have to tie it to a
flagpole and you have to do special
prayers and then it becomes an Aladdin's
limb okay it'll give you anything you
want that's called tinted money
and who's the feel
it's other people okay other people are
your ticket to a success
okay other people can give you
everything you want other people are
like a good field
or other people are like a jewel that
will give you anything you want there's
an excellent
Aladdin's lamp joke which I will share
with all the boys
that I learned in the locker room in
high school
uh
that I'm not gonna teach the ladies and
if you
ever tell Veronica I taught it to me
anyway
uh I will cut your body no uh okay
anyway uh there's this idea that
whatever you want in your life you can
have it
but you have to rub the lamps of other
people you have to do take care of other
people and then everything you want
you will get and I I I can personally
say
I'm not uh great at doing it
but I've tried to do some of it
and it's made my life like a miracle I'm
every every aspect of my life is a
miracle uh everything I mean financially
friends
my work my everything is is
extraordinary so if you can just do a
little bit
of uh this equal rights idea you
Focus this week
on the idea that other people have equal
rights to happiness
the result of that
thinking
is extraordinary it's really
extraordinary you know like you weird
it's strange it's super strange
okay and you you will have a fun happy
life I I'm not so worried about happy
but I want to have fun
uh
and uh I don't know when people promise
you happiness it just seems kind of
boring
uh but fun I'll go for fun you know it's
fun
to have equal rights with other people
it's just really fun
okay and your whole life will be sexy
okay
he says Allah
even in a not spiritual sense okay uh
you get everything you get
in your life
to others okay to others hard work you
know other people are serving you all
day
you know whatever you get
just sitting here
uh is coming from other people so you're
kind of just
paying them back for what they've
already given you okay so he says here
so can
the clothes you have on right now
that green drink
and not the delicious juice
you drank this morning
has come from other people
laughs
the base and uh
dependence yeah yeah dependent
origination so gang's whole book five by
the way it's up to about 500 pages also
um
is is he says
there's a dependent origination here why
there are other people are giving you
everything already
you know forget compassion
and forget uh trying not to be selfish
you owe everybody already
okay why because you had breakfast
and because you're wearing underwear
right now okay I hope
somebody had to get the plant the cotton
or you know pump the oil for those
polyester uh
somebody did a lot of work uh to get you
what you're wearing right now forget
equal rights
you already oh I mean you have a debt
uh by
having eaten this morning
or having had a drink of a green drink
or
wearing clothes
okay you owe somebody
said
and by the way uh
you you owe people like your mom okay
God I don't know and I
I guess it was I had to be 70 to notice
but
the decision to have a child
is it's unbelievable I mean now when I
look at it I I realize you're talking 20
years right
investment and uh no and I mean all your
attention you know I gave up trying to
get work out of these people
um
it's just a kid you know and uh
it's like no seriously and uh
I'm a somebody
in your life
spent all their time in money they
sacrificed uh the prime of their life
and a woman
is giving up her body
you know uh whatever your body was like
before you had kids and after you had
kids you're you're offering your body
to the children and your body becomes a
milk factory
uh on purpose
and and you and you're happy to do it
you know it's very very uh
you're giving up your your whole you
give me not 20 years of your life
and you're giving up your body uh I'm on
ship it said
Not only did uh
people
not only are have people done this for
you in your past lives every person you
ever meet
has been your mom every person you ever
meet gave up their life for you
to take care of you and they
my wife was talking some nonsense
yesterday what was that
um
what was that
yeah
um someone we know got pregnant again
with their
fourth or fifth child
and um
in my and my wife says well uh she just
wants to be happy and I'm like what you
know and she said having a baby is the
happiest thing that can happen to you
and my wife's had two kids and and I'm
like what and she's like yeah
she's just having another baby because
it's the best thing you can do
you know I'm like wow
uh so here I might every person you meet
has been your mom okay and uh nickname
even AMA machampa so that's a little
tricky okay the Tibetan of the next
yeah Amma Amma means mother
I was trying to get into a Tibetan
language class I had had
three weeks of Tibetan I I was trying to
get into a year class on the body chart
on the Buddhist office where I'm like I
was trying to get accepted into the
class
there was a board of three llamas that
were supposed to decide whether I was
qualified
to join the club if my Tibetan was good
enough to join the class for a year
and it was in the Himalayas and um
and I'm like well I can't pass I only
know like five words in tibetan and my
teacher said he was on the board he said
you just come come to the exam you know
and I'm like okay it's a normal exam you
know and I sat down in front of this
board of he's a very high llama he's in
the vajrangini Indonesia
um
and he's and he's I sat down in these
three enormous
and I'm like oh man this is going to be
bad and he says uh I'll take I'll take
this one
and they're like okay and he says okay
I'm gonna ask you Tibetan words and
tell me if you know them you know okay
and I'm like this is hopeless and he
says
this word Amma
Amma
and I'm like
mom
he says you're right
and then he says
and I'm like damn he says you passed
so this word is important to me okay
Amma means mom
okay AMA and uh but here's two months
why
yeah I'm not not your mom
Champa means they they were not your mom
okay he says look
you have an obligation
to treat other people's happiness equal
to your own they have been your mother
countless times you owe them
and then he says even Amma Ma
even when they want your mom you still
owe them God dangy it's like okay come
on they knock it down
they have been
is a beautiful word the Sanskrit is
rakshita
and it means to
take care of someone's needs like a
child like dress them feed them
you know clean up their poo poo uh pay
for them right
cats probably still doing that uh
the the cost of having a kid keeps going
up every week I think
but uh
he says look
everyone's been your mom countless times
but even nowadays
when the there's eight billion people
sitting around only one has been your
mom but the rest are taking care of you
all the time anyway because you're
wearing clothes right now
and you ate this morning and they're
still taking care of you forget this
past life mother thing
we don't even need to think about that
you owe everything
that you have on right now and you owe
the continued existence of the bag and
under your ribs
your stomach to your mom to other people
okay just normal people forget the past
life mom think
yeah and it's very beautiful here uh
then he says
means for example what's sampa
Tibetan oatmeal okay it's great by the
way it's very nutritious you can buy it
nowadays on Amazon
the best one is yarn okay
I I don't know any of the company I just
tried them all uh and uh
Kuma means a little bag
uh with Samba so Tibetan Monks
uh on their belt they wear a little bag
of
uh pre when you call it pre-roasted
barley flour
and you it takes about two spoons to
have breakfast
so when we're studying in the geshi
course we're so busy there's so much
pressure
that you don't have time to eat
breakfast so you carry breakfast
in a little bag on your belt and when
you get
time
if you get like three minutes you mix it
with water and you eat it with your hand
you just go like this
and it tastes delicious if you wash your
hands before
that's why you use them anyway
so he says cook just a little bag of
barley
cereal right
by the way if you have a busy life it's
really it's really helpful I I use it
all the time me and my wife learn to
cooking Cayenne it's good in a blender
first by the way
that's it a sumpa trick
uh look
whatever you had for breakfast this
morning number one modern means someone
planted the field
and when you drive through these rural
areas of Arizona around here you see
what it's like to work on a farm and
it's hard it's really brutal it's a
brutal word I worked for the Farm
Workers for a couple years in my College
days and it's it's brutal where it's
extremely difficult
and it wears you out in a few years okay
somebody
made your food someone grew it okay and
you can have machines and all that but
it's brutal to work anyway it's really
it's brutally difficult work
uh my Jen
then somebody went out and watered all
this crops and and that's brutal work
is a funny word and uh
in India
in the rural in the village Rose
you see people uh rush out in front of
your car
and throw uh weed stalks on the road
and then you drive over them and it
separates the wheat from the Chow
and then they get some fans and they
blow the chaff away and they collect
they try to sweep up the weed before the
next car comes
and it's very dangerous and uh
so Chuke choc means in the old days
you used to lean a
a cow in a circle over the grain
and then it would crush the Grain and
separate the chaff from the wheat okay
so somebody
did that somebody prepared the grain for
you to eat okay
in Sanskrit for 25 dollars
IU IU
I use
immeasurable
like amitaba
measureless life our minta means not
measurable okay so what why does it come
here
yeah the the work that people have put
into your food
and the clothes you have on your back if
you've ever been in a sweatshop in Hong
Kong or something
you know unbelievable just unbelievable
Bangladesh
somebody's there in Bangladesh sewing
your clothes they didn't pop out of
you know a machine somebody had to do it
and it's brutal work you know and people
live and die in those factories
you're wearing it you know
somebody squeezed them for a dollar so
you could save a dollar on Amazon you
know so
the clothes on your back are the result
of great suffering
forget this past life mom thing
if you're wearing clothes right now I
think everybody here as far as I can see
uh
can't say all the online guys
um
me and Sadie were gonna design a suit
uh based on my tree his son's onesies
uh that you could use for Zoom calls and
it's got a tie and a code and then you
just wear your underwear
and the problem is sometimes you have to
stand up
so but we're working on it uh somebody
has
sewn all your clothes and it's hard
brutal work don't
you owe you already own people okay they
already
have a stake in your body because your
body is alive because you wear clothes
and you eat
and in a sense they already deserve part
of your body
because they made it and they keep it
warm
so
why are you hustling them they already
have an investment in your body
okay uh
so I I put a picture of a
well let's do one more let's do one more
paragraph is it so gang is doing it
or or three people
foreign
people try to anyway okay
a couple of days it will get broken all
right
the place where you're sitting right now
whatever house or apartment or Temple
you're sitting in
Samsung
that's the 10 in
cutting content is the long form 10 is
the short form and it means the kindness
of other people okay cotton means the
kindness of other people by the way
The Book cartoon
uh which is this prequel to how Yoga
Works
uh was just published in Ukrainian
and I'd like to thank Rosa
so now it's in Russian and Ukraine and
our publisher in Russia has published it
and uh
Ukrainian Publishers have published it
and the book is for sale
in Ukrainian for one dollar and 99 Cents
okay and uh you can get it if you speak
Ukrainian you can get a copy okay
and if you if you're nice to Rosa she'll
give you one anyway okay uh donate Dion
Central Midland
somebody uh says the place you're
sitting in needs on Tundra many humans
and many animals in Tibet right in 100
years ago
somebody did the excavation
of the dirt to build the house
somebody built the walls
somebody
fashioned the wood somebody made the
boards from trees
somebody was running back and forth with
water to make the cement like that
not just the clothes you're wearing
not just the breakfast you ate this
morning
but if you are
sitting
in a place
okay
that you got to on the road
then you owe somebody somebody you
already owed them
something okay and and that's the house
you're living in this Temple
was built by hand by the first
generation here
and I remember
Allegra
she was how old was she at the time 75
80.
she was bringing she was carrying bricks
and we laid the bricks uh here everybody
pitched in and this so you're sitting
you owe the first generation if you're
in one of these cabins
uh those were built and paid for by the
three-year retreatens each one paid for
their own house and each one built it
but with their own hands and mostly
and uh if you ever meet them you should
thank them right cat
Gelson who else who else we got here
like that okay
oh
yeah dig me a half a house yeah
and they donated them okay they gave up
all their money they built the house
with their own hands and they donated it
so if you meet them you should thank
them you already oh
other people
if you live in a house okay somebody
built it for you and that's that's
unbelievably brutal work I did it for my
dad it's heartburn
somebody did it for my Cafe right Daniel
and it's it's extremely difficult work
and dangerous work sooner or later you
end up getting hurt and
it's hard okay
uh then he says
[Music]
and for a Buddhist monk or none
that's that Shaw okay I think it used to
be a sleeping bag
so it was a warm
long piece of cloth that you could wrap
yourself in and sleep under a tree and
that was the ancient tradition okay and
then now it became sort of a ceremonial
pain in the butt to carry around
Monastery there's a guy who walks around
just to make sure you got your scent on
and gives you a beating if you don't
and they're hot and anyway
so every Monk and every nun has this uh
shawl if you're smart you have a super
thin one
uh in the hot weather San Dion
in Tibet
it was cheaper to make them from more
than cotton because they couldn't grow
cotton that well but they had lots of
sheep
so uh he says look Mumbo means many
sheep pal means wool
somebody had to pluck done means pluck
the wool
from the Sheep Jay gosh she could talk
somebody had to
uh weave it into cloth
kashikits him somebody had to sew it
into a shawl for you
means to wear and chunk means ready to
wear
this is not m-c-h-o-g m-c-h-o-g means
highest this choke means ready to
allowable or ready to wear Okay so
he's just talking about your shirt that
you have on right now okay that's
already
you owe other people for the simplest
piece of clothing you have on right now
I said underwear
okay uh the simplest piece of clothing
that every person in this room has right
now it's already required a lot of work
to create it to distribute it to put it
in the store for you
keep washing it for you do all these
things okay
uh
so we're gonna do a little meditation
here
and I'd like you to practice it today
okay so we have one already I said kind
of we already did it equal rights
meditation
which was to go review
some of the interactions you've had in
the last week or so with other people
and what did they want what did you want
could you have done it better no you
didn't necessarily have a fight
or a disagreement
but could you have done it better
could you have respected their right
equal right
and then the question comes up do they
have an equal right to you to your time
okay I mean we can all agree they have
an equal right to their time or not
you know Veronica you can spend your
time the way you want I'm going to spend
my time the way I want
is that okay you know that's one
question
but now it's getting more complicated do
they have a right
already to your time since you're
dressed this morning and since you ate
this morning and since you're sitting in
a house this morning
maybe they already have more right to
you than you think
okay so that's one meditation you're
going to work on
you know could you approach meetings
with other people
with this idea that maybe they have some
right to your time
okay maybe they have equal right to your
time Buddha thought so right
okay uh
and now we're gonna do another
meditation okay and this is one that we
do in uh DCI
and we call it croissant meditation and
um
it's just you take a simple thing in
your room today okay like I don't know
if you have a piece of toast
or you have a green drink or you you eat
a fruit
s are
a lot of work to me
okay uh take something this afternoon
that you ate
uh okay or something
let's say something you ate okay
and then trace it back
okay trace it back like who brought it
to your cabin
who who bought it at the store
and who put it in the store
and who delivered it to the store
who built the highway that it was
delivered on who built the truck that
carried it across the highway who
planted the tree who watered the tree
look at people how they work in Bowie on
the pecan trees it's brutal
hard work okay so a single piece of food
that's going to be your meditation today
okay we're going to take a single piece
of food
and track it back
track it backwards okay then
we're gonna go deeper
and uh
there is a a meditation called
okay and it's very beautiful
and you you do this backtracking
meditation okay so first
we're gonna do a backtracking meditation
with a physical object
like a piece of food that you eat today
and then when you do your meditations
this afternoon uh you're gonna
do a backtracking meditation
on a piece of food okay or on a piece of
clothing okay and
a lot of it is just imaginary right okay
somebody somewhere brought it to the
store somebody's brought it to my cabin
somebody
planted it
and then I want you to take the fruit
back
because the person who planted it was
using seeds from an orchard that someone
planted before that and someone took
those seeds from an orchard that may be
gone many years ago
the the fruits that you eat
are a result of 50 000 years
of teamwork
okay yeah the stupid banana or apple
that you eat at Diamond Mountain
in this generation
it's a lot of work to get it for you
but
but someone planted the orchard that
that made the Arts in
50 000 years
worked to get you an app
okay some poor caveman figuring it out
since his time or her time
people have been
caring for the seeds and caring for the
fields
to to bring the food to you it's not
it's not the last year it's the last 50
000 years
people have been working for you okay
I just have one or one and a half
employees at my Cafe
and the paperwork
workman's compensation
I mean it's hundreds of pages of
paperwork
you got 50 000 years of paperwork
okay like you got people working for you
for 50 000 years okay take it back okay
uh let's do that right now how much time
I got 10 10. you
know okay to pause for 30 seconds
because we're gonna stop
okay
here we go we're gonna do uh
backtracking
uh
gratitude meditation
and then we're gonna go deeper okay so
this meditation has two meditations all
right ready here we go
let's start with 20 breaths okay
foreign
if you're not sure ask cat okay
so please take one uh piece of food
or in here at Diamond Mountain we've all
in the morning we all get a green drink
or do you fresh juice in
pick pick something
a juice or some piece of bread or rice
or whatever
who brought it to your
home or to the temple here
and thank them
try to imagine what they look like
then imagine where they brought it from
maybe a store
and try to imagine this people working
to
put the food out on the shelves for you
they are working all day
hard work
somebody took your money
somebody made the money somebody made
the paper money somebody made the credit
card somebody did the work for the
programming
for the payment online
hundreds of people
maintaining that
somebody brought the vegetables or fruit
from the farm to the store
I used to do that work in a truck and in
college and uh
it's very difficult work
somebody harvested that
those vegetables are fruit somebody
picked them
for you package them extremely difficult
work
somebody watered the field somebody
fertilized it
somebody plouted
somebody cleared it
we we owed them already our time in our
body
they have a right to some of our time
they have some right to what we do with
our body
the thought to thank them
the thought that they have a right
to sum up my time
also has its history
and this is a second meditation that I'd
like you to do today
this idea
to think about
the idea that someone that other people
might have an equal right to some of my
time
how did that idea start
you know what's the
lineage for that idea so oh well
I heard it from the long room
and then I'd like you to trace mentally
not physically
the the train of thoughts
that led you
to this point in time mentally
your mind
is considering today
the possibility
that other people already have a right
to your time
that we already owe them
some of our time if if we respect the
idea of people's rights
everybody has certain
rights in this world
then those people already have a right
to some of your time because they are
feeding you
they are giving you their time
and they are making your clothes
and they are making your house
and where did this idea come from in the
first place
who said they have an equal right
why am I hearing this right now oh well
I heard about the Islam rim
okay and then you had a thought right
yeah I was thinking I'd like to
hear that chorus I'd I'd like to hear
more about that and then
what were you thinking before that oh I
was curious I was looking around
I feel like there's improvements I could
make
in my life I heard about this Buddhism
stuff and alarm Rim stuff and
where did that thought come from well I
I guess uh
when I was in college I I heard about
Buddhism I I wasn't
learning it but I heard about it
and I was thinking about it and what
happened before that well I was
thinking to go to college
I was thinking to go that there then
what what happened
oh well that come from my family
uh when I was thinking about my mom and
dad used to say about going to college
and
and and then that was sort of an
extension of
my grade school times and and I remember
thinking
about history and about the rest of the
world in my grade school times I can
remember those thoughts
I can remember the thoughts of going to
the first classes in my school I can
remember
especially things that went wrong
in school and I remember how I felt and
and I remember being curious about the
books and
about people what they had to teach and
I remember
the first days before I was only not to
go to school
and I remember what it was like to be
with my mom or my dad my family and I
remember
things we talked about and thoughts I
had
tracing back my mental process I
remember
a day
in my crib
touching a blanket
and feeling how soft it was and being
attracted to the softness I I remember
thinking about the softness
so what I'd like you to do
is two different meditations today one
is
physically
uh pick something you ate something you
wore something you drink
a house that you stayed in
and trace it back
to the people who made the materials who
planted the
to the people who passed on the
knowledge of building houses for 50 000
years
them go back and find new excuses to
thank more people thinking is a very
healthy
happiness creating exercise
and then I want you to notice in a
second meditation today and by the way
that should be
your fresh time so those of you who've
done retreat
you know there's a prime time a day and
you know there's a dull time of day so
prime time
for me it's mid-morning uh
trace it back Trace back your thoughts
and see how far back you can go and if
you work hard
you can trace back to the
to the few years after you were born you
can trace back to
uh when you were an infant a baby
it's possible to trace your mind stream
back
and then eventually you can break
through
uh
the current life and go back into the
darkness of the mushroom places before
this birth
it's possible to trace
your thoughts go in a flow
remember stop being aware
for all time you will be aware
you have a recording in your mind
of past lives you just haven't tried to
access it so while you're working on
tracing back your house or your food or
your clothing
and being grateful
then as a deeper meditation when you
when you're feeling
fresh
Trace back your thoughts
and see if you can trace your thoughts
back
and that's a very very deep
meditation and it has big big uh impact
on being able to see emptiness
okay the exercise
of tracing your thoughts back
and you'll get better and better at it
it's the first day it's kind of clumsy
it's like trying to ride a bicycle
and then after a week
you should be much better at it and that
has
a lot of power
in being able to see emptiness directly
so we're gonna do two
different kinds of backtracking
meditations one is a gratitude backtrack
based on a a piece of fruit or or a
house
or a car and then the other one
is a parallel meditation
where you backtrack your thoughts
and try to see what thought came before
the last one you you can't trace back
every single song
but you can trace back
with gaps you know you can say oh I had
this thought
10 years ago and I had this thought 12
years ago and
and then if you
practice you can work back before this
law
and it's a lot of fun because you
you remember all the Dharma thoughts you
had
okay open your eyes
take a stretch
take a drink Timothy any announcements
or
see you tomorrow
6 a.m World Central Time
which is Bowie Arizona
and it's fun to be with you guys and
thank you for coming online I can see
your smiling beautiful faces
and uh thank you and especially thank
you Francisco and all the stuff
thank you for working so hard especially
translators
and we'll see you tomorrow at 6 00 A.M
back